What keeps us healthy and happy
ما الذى يبقينا سعداء و بصحة جيدة
as we go through life?
ونحن نعيش حياتنا؟
If you were going to invest now
اذا كنت تنوي الآن الإستثمار
in your future best self,
فى مستقبل افضل لك،
where would you put your time and your energy?
أين تُفعِّل وقتك و طاقتك؟
There was a recent survey of millennials
هناك دراسة اجريت مؤخرا على جيل الالفية
asking them what their most important life goals were,
سُئلوا فيها عن اكثر أهداف حياتهم اهمية،
and over 80 percent said
واكثر من 80% قالوا:
that a major life goal for them was to get rich.
أن هدفهم الاساسى في الحياة ان يصبحوا
And another 50 percent of those same young adults
و50% من نفس فئة الشباب
said that another major life goal
قالوا أن الهدف الرئيسى في حياتهم
was to become famous.
أن يصبحوا مشهورين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
And we're constantly told to lean in to work, to push harder
دائما ما نُطالب بالإنكباب على العمل والدفع الى الأمام
and achieve more.
و تحقيق المزيد.
We're given the impression that these are the things that we need to go after
يُخيل لنا أن هذه هي المقاصد التي يجب السعي لها
in order to have a good life.
من أجل بلوغ رغد العيش.
Pictures of entire lives,
صور من حياة بأكملها،
of the choices that people make and how those choices work out for them,
من خيارات الإنسان و كيفية تأثيرها عليه مستقبلك
those pictures are almost impossible to get.
صور كهذه من الصعب الحصول عليها.
Most of what we know about human life
جل ما نعلمه عن الحياة البشرية
we know from asking people to remember the past,
نعلمه من خلال دعوة الناس لاستحضار الماضي،
and as we know, hindsight is anything but 20/20.
و كما نعلم: الإدراك اللاحق للشيء مختلف عن الخوض اللحظي فيه.
We forget vast amounts of what happens to us in life,
لأننا ننسى الكثير مما يحدث لنا في الحياة،
and sometimes memory is downright creative.
والذاكرة في بعض الأحيان تختلق ما لم يحدث.
But what if we could watch entire lives
ولكن ماذا لو كان بامكاننا مراقبة حياة بكاملها،
as they unfold through time?
أثناء تشكلّها مع مرور الوقت ؟
What if we could study people from the time that they were teenagers
ماذا لو استطعنا دراسة الناس من سنّ المراهقة
all the way into old age
إلى سنّ الشيخوخة
to see what really keeps people happy and healthy?
لمعرفة ما يُبقي الناس سعداء وفي صحة جيدة؟
We did that.
لقد فعلنا ذلك.
The Harvard Study of Adult Development
دراسة هارفارد لتطور حياة البالغين
may be the longest study of adult life that's ever been done.
قد تكون أطول دراسة لحياة البالغين تم القيام بها.
For 75 years, we've tracked the lives of 724 men,
خلال 75 عاما، لقد تتبعنا حياة 724 رجلا،
year after year, asking about their work, their home lives, their health,
سنة بعد سنة، نسأل عن أعمالهم وحياتهم الشخصية وصحتهم،
and of course asking all along the way without knowing how their life stories
و بالطبع أثناء ذلك لم نكن نعلم كيف ستنتهي
were going to turn out.
قصص حياتهم.
Studies like this are exceedingly rare.
دراسات كهذه نادرة جدا.
Almost all projects of this kind fall apart within a decade
تقريبا جميع المشاريع من هذا النوع تنهار في غضون عشر سنوات،
because too many people drop out of the study,
لأن الكثير من الناس يتخلى عن الدراسة،
or funding for the research dries up,
أو أن تمويل البحث ينقطع،
or the researchers get distracted,
أو لأن الباحثون تشتت انتباههم،
or they die, and nobody moves the ball further down the field.
أو أنهم يموتون، ولا أحد يواصل الدراسة.
But through a combination of luck
ولكن من خلال مزيج من الحظ
and the persistence of several generations of researchers,
واستمرار جهود عدة أجيال من الباحثين،
this study has survived.
تواصلت هذه الدراسة.
About 60 of our original 724 men
حوالي 60 من أصل 724 رجلا
are still alive,
لا يزالون أحياء،
still participating in the study,
و يواصلون المشاركة في الدراسة،
most of them in their 90s.
معظمهم في التسعينات من أعمارهم.
And we are now beginning to study
وبدأنا الآن في دراسة
the more than 2,000 children of these men.
أكثر من 2000 طفل من هؤلاء الرجال.
And I'm the fourth director of the study.
وأنا المشرف الرابع على الدراسة.
Since 1938, we've tracked the lives of two groups of men.
منذ عام 1938، لقد تتبعنا حياة مجموعتين من الرجال.
The first group started in the study
بدأت المجموعة الأولى في الدراسة
when they were sophomores at Harvard College.
عندما كانوا طلبة بالسنة الثانية في كلية هارفارد.
They all finished college during World War II,
جميعهم أنهوا دراستهم الجامعية خلال الحرب العالمية الثانية،
and then most went off to serve in the war.
وبعد ذلك ذهب أغلبهم للخدمة العسكرية.
And the second group that we've followed
والمجموعة الثانية التي تتبعناها
was a group of boys from Boston's poorest neighborhoods,
كانت مجموعة من الصبية من أفقر الأحياء في بوسطن،
boys who were chosen for the study
الأولاد الذين تم اختيارهم للدراسة
specifically because they were from some of the most troubled
تحديدًا لأنهم كانوا من بعض أكثر العائلات
and disadvantaged families
اضطرابا و حرمانا
in the Boston of the 1930s.
في بوسطن سنة 1930.
Most lived in tenements, many without hot and cold running water.
العديد منهم عاش في شقق من دون مياه جارية باردة وساخنة.
When they entered the study,
عند انخراطهم في هذه الدراسة
all of these teenagers were interviewed.
أجريت مقابلات مع كل من هؤلاء المراهقين.
They were given medical exams.
و أجريت لهم فحوص طبية.
We went to their homes and we interviewed their parents.
ذهبنا إلى منازلهم وأجرينا مقابلات مع والديهم.
And then these teenagers grew up into adults
ثم كبر هؤلاء المراهقين وأصبحوا بالغين
who entered all walks of life.
و خاضوا في تجارب مختلفة في الحياة.
They became factory workers and lawyers and bricklayers and doctors,
أصبحوا عمال مصانع و محامين و بنائين وأطباء،
one President of the United States.
واحد منهم رئيس للولايات المتحدة.
Some developed alcoholism. A few developed schizophrenia.
بعضهم أدمن الكحول و البعض الآخر عانى من إنفصام الشخصية.
Some climbed the social ladder
وصعد البعض السلم الاجتماعي
from the bottom all the way to the very top,
من أسفل إلى أعلى،
and some made that journey in the opposite direction.
وعاش البعض تلك الرحلة في الاتجاه المعاكس.
The founders of this study
مؤسسي هذه الدراسة
would never in their wildest dreams
لم يتصوروا في أقصى طموحاتهم
have imagined that I would be standing here today, 75 years later,
أنني سوف أقف هنا اليوم، بعد مرور 75 عاما،
telling you that the study still continues.
لأقول لكم أن الدراسة لا تزال مستمرة.
Every two years, our patient and dedicated research staff
كل سنتين، فريقنا المتفاني و الصبور
calls up our men and asks them if we can send them
يتصل بالمجموعة ويسألهم إذا كان بإمكاننا أن نرسل لهم
yet one more set of questions about their lives.
مجموعة أخرى من الأسئلة عن حياتهم.
Many of the inner city Boston men ask us,
العديد من الرجال من الأحياء الفقيرة في بوسطن يسألنا،
"Why do you keep wanting to study me? My life just isn't that interesting."
"لماذا ترغبون في دراسة حياتي؟ إنها ليست مثيرة للاهتمام."
The Harvard men never ask that question.
طلاب هارفارد لم يسألوا قط هذا السؤال.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
To get the clearest picture of these lives,
من أجل الحصول على أوضح صورة،
we don't just send them questionnaires.
نحن لا نكتفي بإرسال الإستبيانات.
We interview them in their living rooms.
نحن نُجري مقابلات معهم في غرف معيشتهم.
We get their medical records from their doctors.
نحصل على سجلاتهم الطبية من أطبائهم.
We draw their blood, we scan their brains,
نفحص دمائهم، و نمسح أدمغتهم،
we talk to their children.
نتحدث إلى أطفالهم.
We videotape them talking with their wives about their deepest concerns.
إننا نسجل حديثهم مع زوجاتهم عن أعمق مخاوفهم.
And when, about a decade ago, we finally asked the wives
قبل حوالي عقد من الزمن، أخيرا طلبنا من الزوجات
if they would join us as members of the study,
إن كن يرغبن في الإنضمام لنا كأعضاء في الدراسة،
many of the women said, "You know, it's about time."
العديد منهن قال، "هذا يتطلب وقت."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So what have we learned?
إذًا، ما الذي تعلمناه؟
What are the lessons that come from the tens of thousands of pages
ما هي الدروس التي تعلمناها من عشرات الآلاف من الصفحات؟
of information that we've generated
من المعلومات التي لدينا
on these lives?
عن هذه الحيوات؟
Well, the lessons aren't about wealth or fame or working harder and harder.
حسنا، الدروس ليست حول الثروة أو الشهرة أو العمل بكدّ.
The clearest message that we get from this 75-year study is this:
أوضح رسالة نحصل عليها من هذه الدراسة الممتدة 75 عاما:
Good relationships keep us happier and healthier. Period.
العلاقات الجيدة تجعلنا أكثر سعادة وأكثر صحة. نقطة.
We've learned three big lessons about relationships.
لقد تعلمت ثلاثة دروس كبيرة حول العلاقات.
The first is that social connections are really good for us,
الأول هو أن الصلات الاجتماعية هي فعلا جيدة بالنسبة لنا،
and that loneliness kills.
وأن الوحدة تقتل.
It turns out that people who are more socially connected
وتبين أن الأشخاص المرتبطين أكثر اجتماعيا
to family, to friends, to community,
مع الأسرة والأصدقاء والمجتمع
are happier, they're physically healthier, and they live longer
هم أكثر سعادة، أكثر صحة جسديًا، ويعيشون حياة أطول
than people who are less well connected.
من الذين هم أقل إرتباطا.
And the experience of loneliness turns out to be toxic.
وتبين أن تجربة الوحدة سامة.
People who are more isolated than they want to be from others
الناس الذين هم أكثر عزلة
find that they are less happy,
وجدوا أنهم أقل سعادة،
their health declines earlier in midlife,
تتراجع صحتهم أسرع في منتصف العمر،
their brain functioning declines sooner
أداء أدمغتهم يتراجع عاجلا
and they live shorter lives than people who are not lonely.
ويعيشون حياة أقصر من الناس الذين يحاطون بأحبائهم
And the sad fact is that at any given time,
والحقيقة المحزنة هي أنه في أي وقت من الأوقات،
more than one in five Americans will report that they're lonely.
أكثر من واحد من كل خمسة أميركيين يقر بأنه وحيد.
And we know that you can be lonely in a crowd
ونحن نعلم أنه يمكن أن تكون وحيدا في حشد من الناس
and you can be lonely in a marriage,
ويمكنك أن تكون وحيدا في الزواج،
so the second big lesson that we learned
لذلك الدرس الكبير الثاني الذي تعلمناه
is that it's not just the number of friends you have,
أن الأمر ليس مجرد عدد من الاصدقاء لديك،
and it's not whether or not you're in a committed relationship,
وليس إن كنت في علاقة أم لا،
but it's the quality of your close relationships that matters.
ولكن نوعية علاقاتك هي ما يهم.
It turns out that living in the midst of conflict is really bad for our health.
وتبين أن العيش في خضم الصراع سيئ جدًا لصحتنا.
High-conflict marriages, for example, without much affection,
على سبيل المثال، الزواج كثيرالصراع قليل المودة،
turn out to be very bad for our health, perhaps worse than getting divorced.
سيئ جدا لصحتنا، ربما أسوأ من الطلاق.
And living in the midst of good, warm relationships is protective.
و العيش في خضم العلاقات الدافئة جيد ووقائي.
Once we had followed our men all the way into their 80s,
بعد أن تتبعننا هؤلاء الرجال إلى عمر الثمانين،
we wanted to look back at them at midlife
أردنا أن ننظر إلى الوراء إلى منتصف أعمارهم
and to see if we could predict
ونرى ما اذا كان يمكن التنبؤ
who was going to grow into a happy, healthy octogenarian
بمن سيكبر ليصبح رجلا سعيدا و في صحة جيدة في الثمانين من عمره
and who wasn't.
و من لن يكون ذلك حاله.
And when we gathered together everything we knew about them
وعندما جمعنا معا كل ما عرفناه عنهم
at age 50,
في سن ال 50،
it wasn't their middle age cholesterol levels
لم تكن مستويات الكوليسترول في منتصف العمر
that predicted how they were going to grow old.
التي تنبأت كيف سيكبرون
It was how satisfied they were in their relationships.
بل مدى رضاهم في علاقاتهم.
The people who were the most satisfied in their relationships at age 50
الناس الذين كانوا أكثر رضا في علاقاتهم في سن ال50
were the healthiest at age 80.
كانوا الأكثر صحة في سن ال 80.
And good, close relationships seem to buffer us
ويبدو أن العلاقات الوثيقة جيدة للتخفيف علينا
from some of the slings and arrows of getting old.
من صعوبات تقدم السن.
Our most happily partnered men and women
الأزواج الأكثر سعادة
reported, in their 80s,
ذكروا في سن 80
that on the days when they had more physical pain,
أن في الأيام التي عانوا فيها من الألم المادي،
their mood stayed just as happy.
مزاجهم بقي سعيدا.
But the people who were in unhappy relationships,
ولكن الناس الذين كانوا في علاقات غير سعيدة،
on the days when they reported more physical pain,
في الأيام التي عانوا فيها من الألم المادي،
it was magnified by more emotional pain.
تضخم ذلك من قبل الألم العاطفي.
And the third big lesson that we learned about relationships and our health
والدرس الكبير الثالث الذي تعلمناه حول العلاقات و الصحة
is that good relationships don't just protect our bodies,
أن العلاقات الجيدة لا تحمي فقط أجسادنا،
they protect our brains.
إنها تحمي أدمغتنا.
It turns out that being in a securely attached relationship
وتبين أن علاقة عميقة التعلق
to another person in your 80s is protective,
إلى شخص آخر في ال80 وقائية،
that the people who are in relationships
أن الناس الذين هم في علاقات
where they really feel they can count on the other person in times of need,
حيث حقا يشعرون بأنهم يستطيعون الاعتماد على الشخص الآخر في أوقات الحاجة،
those people's memories stay sharper longer.
ذكريات هؤلاء الناس تبقى أكثر وضوحا لفترة أطول.
And the people in relationships
والناس الذين هم في علاقات
where they feel they really can't count on the other one,
حيث يشعرون أنه في الحقيقة لا يمكنهم الإعتماد على الآخر،
those are the people who experience earlier memory decline.
هؤلاء هم الناس الذين يعانون مبكرا من تراجع الذاكرة.
And those good relationships, they don't have to be smooth all the time.
وهذه العلاقات الجيدة، يمكن أن تكون غير سلسة أحيانا
Some of our octogenarian couples could bicker with each other
بعض الأزواج الثمانينين لدينا يمكن أن يجاهد بعضهم البعض
day in and day out,
يوم بعد يوم،
but as long as they felt that they could really count on the other
ولكن طالما أنهم شعروا أن بإمكانهم الاعتماد حقا على الآخر
when the going got tough,
عندما تأزم الوضع،
those arguments didn't take a toll on their memories.
لم تؤثر تلك الخلافات سلبا على ذاكرتهم.
So this message,
لذلك فالعبرة،
that good, close relationships are good for our health and well-being,
العلاقات الوثيقة جيدة لصحتنا ورفاهيتنا،
this is wisdom that's as old as the hills.
و هذه حكمة قديمة جدا.
Why is this so hard to get and so easy to ignore?
لماذا هذا يصعب فهمه ويسهُل تجاهله؟
Well, we're human.
حسنا، نحن بشر.
What we'd really like is a quick fix,
ما نوده حقا هو الحصول على حل سريع،
something we can get
شيء يمكن أن نحصل عليه
that'll make our lives good and keep them that way.
يجعل حياتنا جيدة و يُُمكنُنا من الإحتفاظ بها هكذا.
Relationships are messy and they're complicated
العلاقات فوضوية و معقدة
and the hard work of tending to family and friends,
والعمل الجاد للميل إلى العائلة والأصدقاء،
it's not sexy or glamorous.
ليس جذابا أو براقا.
It's also lifelong. It never ends.
إنه مدى الحياة. ولا ينتهى ابدا.
The people in our 75-year study who were the happiest in retirement
الناس في دراستنا الذين كانوا أسعد في التقاعد
were the people who had actively worked to replace workmates with new playmates.
هم الذين عملوا بنشاط ليحل رفقاءهم الجدد محل زملاء العمل.
Just like the millennials in that recent survey,
تماما مثل جيل الألفية في تلك الدراسة الحديثة،
many of our men when they were starting out as young adults
كثير من رجالنا عندما كانوا شبابا
really believed that fame and wealth and high achievement
اعتقدوا حقا أن الشهرة والثروة والإنجاز العالي
were what they needed to go after to have a good life.
هي ما يحتاجونه للحصول على حياة جيدة.
But over and over, over these 75 years, our study has shown
ولكن، على مدى هذه السنوات 75، أظهرت دراستنا مرارا وتكرارا
that the people who fared the best were the people who leaned in to relationships,
أن الأشخاص ذوي الحظ الأفضل كانوا الناس الذين إهتموا بالعلاقات،
with family, with friends, with community.
مع الأسرة، مع الأصدقاء، مع المجتمع.
So what about you?
ماذا عنك؟
Let's say you're 25, or you're 40, or you're 60.
دعونا نقول أنك في 25، أو في 40، أو في 60 من العمر.
What might leaning in to relationships even look like?
كيف ترى العلاقات؟
Well, the possibilities are practically endless.
حسنا، الاحتمالات لا حصر لها عمليا.
It might be something as simple as replacing screen time with people time
قد يكون شيء بسيط مثل استبدال الوقت أمام الشاشة بالوقت مع الناس
or livening up a stale relationship by doing something new together,
أو تنشيط علاقة قديمة عن طريق القيام بشيء جديد معا،
long walks or date nights,
التمشي لمسافات طويلة أو مواعدة ليلية،
or reaching out to that family member who you haven't spoken to in years,
أو التواصل مع أفراد الأسرة الذين لم تتحدث معهم منذ سنوات،
because those all-too-common family feuds
لأن تلك النزاعات العائلية
take a terrible toll
تجرّ خسائر فادحة
on the people who hold the grudges.
على الناس الذين يحملون الأحقاد.
I'd like to close with a quote from Mark Twain.
أود أن أنهي حديثي باقتباس من مارك توين.
More than a century ago,
منذ أكثر من قرن من الزمان،
he was looking back on his life,
عندما نظر إلى الوراء في حياته،
and he wrote this:
وكتب هذا:
"There isn't time, so brief is life,
"مختصرة هي الحياة، ليس هناك وقت
for bickerings, apologies, heartburnings, callings to account.
للخصومات و الاعتذارات و الانتقامات
There is only time for loving,
هناك متسع من الوقت للمحبة فقط،
and but an instant, so to speak, for that."
للحظة فقط، إذا جاز التعبير".
The good life is built with good relationships.
الحياة الجيدة تُبنى بالعلاقات الجيدة.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)